Welcome back to the radio day in the lab.
실험실의 라디오 방송에 잘 오셨어요
More to do.
할 일이 더 있어요
Let's keep going.
계속하죠
Where we left off is we had just built a simple user interface that was calling an LLM and telling a
마지막으로 본 것은 간단한 사용자 인터페이스를 구축한 것이었죠 LLM을 호출하고 아주
very, uh, good joke.
재미있는 농담을 했어요
Uh, let's keep going with this.
계속 진행하죠
What we're going to do next is ask for the, uh, assistant to respond in markdown, uh, as a way of,
다음으로 할 일은 보조에게 가격 인하를 요청하는 겁니다 보다 나은 사용자
uh, um, getting better looking user interfaces.
인터페이스를 얻는 방법으로요
Um, and wouldn't it be nice if we wanted to show results in gradio with good formatting written in
그러디오에서 좋은 서식을 마크다운으로 써서 결과를 보여주면 좋지 않을까요?
If we could just have that instead of text box, just replace it with the word markdown, and then the
텍스트 상자 대신에 마크다운으로 대체할 수 있다면 완벽한 형식의
output would be in perfectly formatted markdown.
마크다운으로 결과물이 나올 거예요
That would be great wouldn't it?
그러면 정말 좋겠죠?
Wouldn't it be nice?
좋지 않을까요?
You're probably getting the idea here.
무슨 말인지 아시겠죠?
Things just really are.
정말 그래요
This good.
이 정도면 돼요
Uh, So let's say your message.
메시지를 생각해 보죠
Let's say, um.
예를 들어 볼게요
Um, how do I get from Times Square to Times Square like that to Grand Central?
어떻게 타임스스퀘어에서 그랜드 센트럴까지 가죠? Get you get the time
I've got a question for New York navigation.
뉴욕 항법팀에 질문이 있어요
Let's see how it does.
어떻게 되나 보죠
It's thinking about that.
그 생각을 하는 거예요
And there we go.
다 됐어요
Here's a response.
이렇게 대답하죠
And you can see to get from Times Square to Grand Central Terminal in New York City, it figured out
타임스퀘어에서 뉴욕 그랜드 센트럴 터미널까지 가는 길은 모두 제 말을 이해했어요
that's what I was talking about.
Get it
Follow these steps and you can see it's good headings.
이 단계를 따라가면 멋진 헤딩이 나와요
And it's got a nice sub bullets and numbers and all the rest of it, as described in the markdown that
괜찮은 sub 탄환과 번호도 있고 GPT 4에서 받은 표시된 모든
came back from GPT four.
것이 있어요.
Oh very easy, very nice.
아주 쉽고 좋네요
Let's have a look at what else we can do.
다른 방법도 한번 살펴보죠
Uh, streaming.
스트리밍요
Streaming is something we got used to last time.
스트리밍은 지난번에도 익숙해졌잖아요
So can we stream results back to Gradio user interfaces, just as we did when it was coming back into
그라디오 유저 인터페이스로 결과를 스트리밍할 수 있나요? 주피터 출력 셀로 되돌아올
a Jupyter output cell.
때 했던 것처럼요
So here we go.
자, 시작하죠
We change our function.
함수를 바꾸죠
It used to be the message GPT.
예전엔 GPT라는 메시지였죠
Now we're making it stream GPT.
이제 GPT 스트림으로 만들 거예요
Different function.
함수가 달라요
And the key thing is that this isn't actually a function.
중요한 건 이게 함수가 아니란 거죠
It's a generator in that it's going to end by yielding a result.
발전기 같은 거예요 결과적으로 끝날 거예요
And Gradio is going to detect that we're giving it a generator, not a function.
그라디오는 우리가 함수 기능을 부여한 게 아니라 발전기를 줬다는 걸 눈치챌 거예요
And because of that, Gradio is automatically going to be iterative and decide to fill in, um, piece
그 때문에 그라디오는 자동으로 반복적으로 재생되고 발전기에서 돌아오는
by piece as it comes back from this generator.
부분마다 채워넣게 되죠
So usual story.
늘 있는 일이죠
I create the messages and then you'll remember this time it's the same API call, but we pass in stream
메시지를 생성하면 이번엔 같은 API 호출이란 걸 기억하실 겁니다 하지만 스트리밍에서 넘긴 건
equals true.
true죠
You remember how Claude does it?
클로드가 어떻게 하는지 알죠?
Hopefully you do.
그러길 바라요
With Claude, you don't have an attribute, but instead you call dot stream instead of dot create.
클로드는 특성이 없어요 대신 .Create 대신 .Timle을 호출하죠
But otherwise it's very similar.
그 외에는 아주 비슷해요
So one thing that's worth noting here.
여기서 주목할 게 하나 있어요
Just a tiny subtlety with Gradio.
그래디오와 아주 미묘하게 일치하죠
When you are streaming back the results to Gradio, you don't stream back chunk by chunk of the results.
결과를 그라디오로 스트리밍할 때 결과를 하나씩 스트리밍하지 않아요
You have to stream back the entire cumulative result so far and stream back a longer and longer cumulative
지금까지 누적된 결과를 전부 스트리밍해야 해요 그리고 누적 결과를 점점 더 오랫동안 스트리밍해야
result.
하죠
So you can see what I'm doing is I'm I'm sort of starting with an empty string.
제가 뭘 하는지 보이시죠 빈 문자열로 시작해요
And then for each chunk I'm adding that in and then yielding the total cumulative result so far.
각각의 덩어리에 추가하고 지금까지 누적된 총 결과를 산출하는 거죠
Um, and if you don't do that, what you'll see is each individual chunk will appear in the output cell
그렇게 하지 않으면 출력 셀에 각 덩어리가 나타났다가 사라지고
and then disappear and will be replaced by something else.
다른 것으로 대체되죠
So you have to do it this way.
이렇게 해야 해요
If you don't see what I mean, try doing yield chunk instead of yield result.
무슨 뜻인지 모르겠다면 수확 결과 대신 수확량 덩어리를 입력해 보세요
Sorry.
미안해요
Yield chunk .0. delta dot content.
큰 덩어리를요 0살요 델타 닷 콘텐츠요
Uh.
네
And you'll see exactly what I mean.
무슨 말인지 알게 될 거예요
It's not not going to look good.
보기 안 좋을 거예요
Uh, anyway, that is our stream GPT uh, and wouldn't it be nice if all we needed to do was replace
어쨌든 이게 스트림 GPT입니다 메시지 GPT였던 함수를 스트림으로 대체하기만 하면
the the function that it used to be message GPT with stream, GPT and Gradio just figured out the rest.
좋을 것 같은데요 GPT와 Gadio가 나머지를 해결했네요
It figured out that okay, this is a generator, not a function.
이건 발전기일 뿐 함수가 아니란 걸 알아냈죠
Therefore, they're going to want to stream back results.
따라서 결과를 스트리밍하길 원할 거예요
Therefore, I need to have a sort of typewriter animation style effect.
그래서 타자기 애니메이션 같은 효과를 내야 했죠
Let's see if it really can be that simple.
그렇게 간단한지 확인해 보죠
Can it be that simple?
그렇게 간단해요?
Here we go.
시작할게요
Uh, how do I get from Times Square to Grand Central?
Get it, get it, get it, it 타임스스퀘어에서 그랜드 센트럴까지 어떻게 가죠?
And there we go.
다 됐어요
Of course, it's that simple.
그럼요, 간단하죠
Of course it is.
당연히 그렇겠죠
Streams the results.
결과를 내보내죠
They look great.
잘 어울려요
Markdown looks fantastic.
마크다운이 아주 멋져요
Uh, so, uh, of course it wouldn't be doing my job if I didn't show you how easy it is with Claude
클로드와의 관계가 얼마나 쉬운지 보여드리지 않으면 제 일이 아니겠죠
I mentioned it before, and now you can see there is Claude's API call.
전에 언급했었죠 클로드의 API 호출이 저기 있는 게 보이시죠
It's very similar.
아주 비슷해요
You call dot stream, you don't pass in the parameter.
닷 스트림을 호출하면 매개변수에서 통과 못 해요
You remember that you do have to specify max tokens and the system message goes in separately.
최대 토큰을 지정해야 한다는 걸 기억하세요 시스템 메시지는 따로 보내지죠
Otherwise very similar.
그 외에는 아주 비슷해요
The streaming back is just for results as stream.
스트리밍은 결과만을 위한 거죠
So with result as stream a context manager.
결과는 스트림으로서 컨텍스트 관리자죠
And then we yield the full response just as before.
그럼 전처럼 완전한 반응을 보여드리죠
And at this point it's going to be boringly simple.
이 시점에서 지루할 정도로 간단해요
You get the joke.
Get it, get it, get it, get it, it! 농담 이해하죠?
You simply pass in that function instead.
그 함수를 전달하는 거죠
And now we are talking to Claude instead.
지금은 클로드랑 얘기하고 있어요
We'll ask it the same question though.
우리도 같은 질문을 할 거예요
How do I get from Times Square to Grand Central?
Get it, get it, get it, it, it, it, it! 타임스스퀘어에서 그랜드 센트럴까지 어떻게 가죠?
And here comes Claude's response, a bit shorter, just two options, but nicely structured.
클로드의 답장은 비트보다 짧고 두 가지밖에 없지만 구조가 잘 짜여 있죠
Nicely formatted.
서식이 멋지네요
Very good indeed.
정말 훌륭해요
Um, so we can take this one step forwards by having the ability to choose either GPT or Claude.
GPT나 클로드 중 하나를 선택함으로써 한 걸음 더 나아갈 수 있어요
But I'm going to get to that in the very next session.
Get in get은 다음 세션에서 다룰게요
So hang on in there.
조금만 더 버텨요